Guide to the New-York Historical Society Public Programs and Education Records 1941-2014 (bulk, 1984-2004) NYHS-RG 23
New-York Historical Society
New-York Historical Society public programs and education records
1941-2014 (bulk, 1984-2004)
New-York Historical Society
NYHS-RG 23
37.71 Linear feet in 43 boxes (29 record cartons, 11 document boxes, and 3 other boxes of various sizes)
The New-York Historical Society public programs and education records include files related to the creation, publicity, outreach, funding, management, and implementation of N-YHS's programs, principally for the years 1984-1992. Regular programming included, among other things, panel discussions, lectures, concerts, films, museum gallery tours, teacher/educator workshops, and special collaborations such as arts-in-education classes or programs for at-risk students.
Biographical/Historical Note
In 1928, New-York Historical Society's Act of Incorporation was amended by the state legislature to recognize the organization's mission as including "educational purposes." This had important tax advantages, but it also reflected the vision of the chief executive officer at the time, Librarian Alexander J. Wall, to expand public access to N-YHS's resources. Presentations on historical topics, public access to the galleries and even school tours had long been a feature of N-YHS's programs, but financial constraints limited these. In the late 1930s, with the receipt of the large Thompson bequest, the renovation and expansion of the Central Park West building, and the hiring of a small staff to direct educational programs, the programs could, and did, expand, even to include concerts and films, among other initiatives.
Librarian Wall died in 1944, but his son, Alexander J. Wall, Jr., became N-YHS's Head of Education and Public Relations in 1946 when he returned from the military at the close of World War II. With the exception of the 1950s, this connection between programs and public relations continued until educational programs were cutback in the early 1980s in the face of financial difficulties. This cutback was short-lived, and in 1983 N-YHS hired Carole Slatkin as Director of Public Programs. Over the course of the next several years, programming would expand aggressively in quantity and in N-YHS's willingness to move in new, even provocative, directions. It is this period from about 1984 through 1992 that is the principal focus of the current content of the public programs and education record group.
Carole Slatkin remained Director of Public Programs until about 1989 when she was replaced by Rae Alexander-Minter. Slatkin continued to work on program-related projects until she left N-YHS. Stephanie Starr worked as an Associate for Public Programs in the 1980s, replaced when she left N-YHS about 1989 by Erika Sanger. Judith M. Giuriceo became an Associate for School Programs about 1990. Jane Lattes was the docent/volunteer coordinator until about 1989 when Marion Galison took that role. Alisa Aydin was an administrative assistant in the unit around 1990. All these individuals, in their active management of programming activities, appear in the documents of the record group. In January 1993, at the height of N-YHS's fiscal crisis, the galleries closed to the public, bringing an end to the program staff and explaining the clear break in the records here. The galleries re-opened in mid-1995 with a renewed emphasis on education and public programs, one that has greatly developed well beyond even the significant initiatives of the late 1980s-1990s.
Following is some background on certain unique initiatives for which there is extensive documentation in the record group:
Summer Institute: This teacher workshop was conducted for three summers (1987-1989). Centered on the theme "Teaching the Constitution," the workshop accepted about fifteen educators each year from public and private schools of various grades to participate in three weeks of readings, lectures, and discussions. Each teacher developed a lesson plan as a final project based on knowledge gained during the workshop and using N-YHS's library resources. The program was overseen by Carole Slatkin, though directed by Gail Sussman Marcus, who was hired specifically to focus on the Institute's development and implementation.
U.S. Constitution Programs: The Summer Institute used the Constitution as its organizing focus at least in part because 1987 was the Constitution's bicentennial. N-YHS engaged in several educational programs drawing on this anniversary and the associated exhibition it mounted, Government by Choice: Inventing the Constitution. Among these programs were U.S. Constitution on the Air (a series of radio programs and related curriculum guide) and a set of teacher programs called The Bicentennial Connection. These initiatives were done in partnership with others, including a New York City educational program called Impact II, and with funding from the Commission on the Bicentennial of the U.S. Constitution.
Why History?: This series of programs started in 1990 as an initiative to examine the meaning of history and its relationship to contemporary issues in America. It attempted to thematically link multiple events across three program components: panel discussions, film series, and music presentations. The 1991 series added a sub-theme: Why History? Race and Class. 1992's sub-theme was: Why History? What is American?
New York Tapes: This was a pilot program, or prototype, conducted in August 1990, that videotaped New Yorkers at various places in the city, telling personal stories. It was produced by video artist Wendy Clarke and directed by Gary Glassman in conjunction with N-YHS, with funding by the DeWitt Wallace-Reader's Digest Fund.
Lab School Programs: This arts-in-education program was begun in 1991 as a collaboration between N-YHS and the William J. O'Shea Junior High School, or IS 44, using the Luman Reed Gallery as its centerpiece. In 1992, a second project was started, initially to study local history, but eventually to focus on Seneca Village. In addition to IS 44, collaborations included Central Park East Secondary School and the Trinity School.
Liberty Scholars Program: This was begun in October 1990, funded by the State Education Department as part of the Governor's Liberty Partnerships Program concerning at-risk students. Conducted in collaboration with Bank Street College, the program included eight Saturday sessions during which the students visited N-YHS to tour, meet professionals, learn about the various operations of libraries and museums, and to work on a local history project.
Returning the Gift: This project included various activities in order that North American Native writers might share their work. N-YHS was one of four outreach sites.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Arrangement Note
The New-York Historical Society public programs and education records are organized in the following series:
Series I. Program Files
Series II. Teaching Resources
Series III. Docent John B. Snook Files
Scope and Contents Note
The New-York Historical Society public programs and education records include files related to the creation, publicity, outreach, funding, management, and implementation of NYHS's programs, principally for the years 1984-1992. Regular programming included, among other things, panel discussions, lectures, concerts, films, and museum gallery tours. The programs also included school age education programs, such as tours for schoolchildren and teacher/educator workshops, as well as special collaborations such as arts-in-education classes or programs for at-risk students. The record group includes documents such as correspondence, plans, scripts, background information for docents, evaluations, statistical reports (e.g., attendance), logistical arrangements (e.g., group reservations, docent scheduling, expenses), classroom teacher resources, brochures, funding requests, and more. Special programs well-documented in the record group are, among others, the array of activities conducted by N-YHS in connection with the 1987 bicentennial of the U.S. Constitution and the Why History? series (1990-1992) that sought to explore historical themes in direct relation to present day concerns. The record group also holds the reference files of John B. Snook, a docent at N-YHS from 1995-2004.
Accruals Note
Further accruals to the record group are expected over time.
Related Archival Materials Note
This finding aid relates to just one record group of the New-York Historical Society archives. For information about the other record groups and for overall information about the archives, please see the Guide to the New-York Historical Society Archives (NYHS-RG Archives). Other record groups that are processed and are especially related to the New-York Historical Society public programs and education records (NYHS-RG 23) are as follows:
New-York Historical Society audiovisual (NYHS-RG 28) includes audiotapes and videotapes of some of the programs documented in this record group. The tapes, however, are currently restricted from use because they are the original and only known copies; given their age, they are fragile and the N-YHS library does not have the necessary playback equipment.
Museum outreach programs; Outreach programs in history; Resource programs (Education) -- New York (State) -- New York.; Museum docents -- New York (State) -- New York.; United States Constitution Bicentennial, 1987-1991; Learned institutions and societies -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- History -- Societies, etc.; United States -- History -- Study and teaching.; New-York Historical Society. Education Department; New-York Historical Society. Public Programs Department; New-York Historical Society -- Archives
- Series I. Program Files, 1941-2014 (bulk, 1984-1992); 32.92 Linear feet
  Arrangement Note
  The series is arranged in rough topical order. During processing in 2016, the files were found with little overall arrangement, accordingly much of the arrangement and categorizations of material were established in 2016 by the processing archivist. Files on specific special programs that had especially extensive files appear first in the container list. These are followed by more general sets of files. Notes at the box level provide further information about the content and the more substantive material found there.
  Scope and Contents Note
  The Program Files series includes records related to the creation, publicity, outreach, funding, and implementation of N-YHS's public programs, principally for the years 1984-1992. Regular programming included, among other things, panel discussions, lectures, concerts, films, and gallery tours. The programs also included school age education programs, such as tours for schoolchildren and teacher/educator workshops, as well as special collaborations such as arts-in-education classes or programs for at-risk students. See the Historical Note above for further description of some of the specific programs well-represented in the series.
  The series appears to be, in general, a compilation of records from at least seven individuals: Directors of Public Programs Carole Slatkin (1984-1989) and Rae Alexander-Minter (1989-1993), Associates for Public Programs Stephanie Starr (until about 1989) and Erika Sanger (about 1989-1993), Associate for School Programs Judith M. Giuriceo (started about 1990), and docent/volunteer coordinators Jane Lattes (until about 1989) and Marion Galison (1989-1993). The series includes program descriptions, planning documents, correspondence and memos, publicity, attendance counts, logistical records (e.g., group reservation forms, docent schedules), program evaluations, curriculum or presentation materials for school groups, background texts and some training or informational content for docents. The specific programs covered are wide-ranging and further detail on scope and content at the box level is given below in the container list.
  Although the bulk of the series includes documents from 1984-1992, there is a small amount of earlier program material, principally publicity-related; this is noted in the container list. For later periods, there are also publicity brochures from the early 2000s.
  - Summer Institute 1987 (16 folders), 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1-16)
  - Summer Institute 1988 (26 folders), 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 17-42)
  - Summer Institute 1989 (22 folders), 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 1-22)
  - Summer Institute. General Files (16 folders), 1987-1989 (Offsite-box 2, Folder 23-38)
    General Note
    Includes files with documents relating to Institutes from multiple years (e.g. speaker biographies, participant lists, correspondence templates, etc.) and miscellaneous materials.
  - Summer Institute. Final Projects (23 folders), 1988-1989 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 1-23)
  - Summer Institute. Resources (11 folders), 1986-1988 (Offsite-box 3, Folder 24-35)
    Includes miscellaneous print matter (not produced by N-YHS) related to the Constitution, materials produced in connection with the Bicentennial, and teaching resources. Includes an artifact: cards depicting images and biographies of the delegates to the 1787 Constitutional Convention.
  - Summer Institute. Readings & Resources (38 of 65 folders), 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 4, Folder 1-38)
    This box and the next includes files (most of which appear to be those of Gail Marcus) of Institute readings and other reference matter.
  - Summer Institute. Readings & Resources (27 of 65 folders), 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 1-27)
  - "We the People": Our Living Constitution. N-YHS Discovery Book, 1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 28)
  - Government by Choice: Inventing the Constitution (4 folders), 1986-1987 (Offsite-box 5, Folder 29-32)
    Includes a folder with documents concerning the exhibition of this name held at N-YHS from September 17, 1987-January 17, 1988. Also includes files of programs related to the exhibition including education/class tie-ins and an audiovisual slide show. See also the box of Exhibition Files (1 of 2) below; this holds several folders on program tie-ins to the Constitution Bicentennial and exhibition.
  - U.S. Constitution Bicentennial Programs (20 folders), 1986-1989 (Offsite-box 6, Folder 1-20)
    Includes various programs related to the Constitution, including "United States Constitution on the Air," Bicentennial Connection, mock debates, lectures, and others. Some done in partnership with the IMPACT II program of the New York City Board of Education and funded by the Commission on the Bicentennial of the Constitution.
  - IMPACT II Materials / Arts & Cultural Education Network (16 folders), 1985-1991 (Offsite-box 16, Folder 1-16)
    Includes general material concerning these New York City Board of Education programs and N-YHS's connection to them.
  - Why History? 1990 (57 of 79 folders), 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 7, Folder 1-57)
  - Why History? 1990 (22 of 79 folders), 1989-1990 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 1-22)
  - Why History? Race & Class 1991 (50 of 83 folders), 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 8, Folder 23-72)
  - Why History? Race & Class 1991 (33 of 83 folders), 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 1-33)
  - Why History? What is American? 1992 (42 of 97 folders), 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 9, Folder 34-75)
  - Why History? What is American? 1992 (44 of 97 folders), 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 1-44)
  - Why History? What is American? 1992 (11 of 97 folders) (Offsite-box 11, Folder 1-11)
    This box holds transcripts of the lectures.
  - Why History? General Files (7 folders), 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 10, Folder 45-51)
    Includes folders that include materials related to all or most of the three Why History? years/series.
  - Collecting & Connoiseurship Symposium (5 folders), 1982, 1984 (Offsite-box 12, Folder 1-5)
  - New York Walks (1 of 2 boxes), 1987-1988 (Offsite-box 13, Folder 1-13)
    These were walking tours of Manhattan. Includes narratives, publicity, clippings, route maps, etc.
  - New York Walks (2 of 2 boxes), 1987-1989, 1992 (Offsite-box 14, Folder 1-9)
  - New York Tapes (41 folders), 1990 (Offsite-box 15, Folder 1-41)
    Includes narrative, location permissions, interviewee releases, budgets, logistics, etc.
  - Imagining the New World: Columbian Iconography Programs (50 folders), 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 17, Folder 1-50)
    Includes drafts and finals of teacher's packet, program evaluations, background material, and other documents concerning tie-ins to this exhibition.
  - Lab School Programs (41 of 68 folders), 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 18, Folder 1-41)
    This box holds general files on Lab Schools and the files for the Luman Reed Gallery project. The general files include reference to the Seneca Village project, which is primarily in the following box.
  - Lab School Programs (27 of 68 folders), 1991-1992 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 1-27)
    Includes the Seneca Village Lab School project files.
  - Bank Street College / Liberty Scholars (12 folders), 1990-1991 (Offsite-box 19, Folder 28-39)
  - Returning the Gift / Six Nations (Iroquois) Census Reprint (17 folders), 1992 (Offsite-box 27, Folder 1-17)
  - General Program Files (1 of 5 boxes), 1972-1991 (Offsite-box 20, Folder 1-49)
    Generally, this set of five boxes appears to hold material primarily from the files of Carole Slatkin, Rae Alexander-Minter, Erika Sanger, and Stephanie Starr. This box includes, among other subjects, a survey of N-YHS visitors (1988), statistics (1984-1989), budgets (1986-1991), reports, and files on various tours, lectures, St. Nicholas festivals, and other programs from the late 1980s. There is a small amount of material from the 1960s-1970s, principally related to concerts.
  - General Program Files (2 of 5 boxes), 1985-1990 (Offsite-box 21, Folder 1-54)
    Includes, among other subjects, Wilkinson toy collection programs, New York: Past, Present & Future lecture series, Shelburne Sampler-related programs, wine-tasting tours and other trips, and Angela Brown recital.
  - General Program Files (3 of 5 boxes), 1987-1992 (Offsite-box 22, Folder 1-41)
    Includes, among other subjects, concerts (Mexican, Virtuosi Quintet); Associated Solo Artists' development of a musical work based on Thomas Cole's Course of Empire (the file includes an audiotape); survey from open house for scholars of American history and art; tours and programs associated with Paris 1889 exhibition; a Con Edison Black History Book Cover Program (with a photograph of Dr. Rae Alexander-Minter with students at IS 44); Jewish Museum at N-YHS; Art What Thou Eat notes and discussion guide; Luman Reed projects; and management reports on public programs, FY1990-FY1992.
  - General Program Files (4 of 5 boxes), 1990-1992 (Offsite-box 23, Folder 1-50)
    Includes, among other subjects, tour attendance statistics (1991); audience trends at New York museums; Audubon-related programs; Simon Schama lecture; programs in connection with McKim, Mead & White exhibition (with questionnaires); Day Without Art; program administration (ticketing, audiovisual requirements, mailings); and questionnaires from "History for Adults: Objectives & Strategies."
  - General Program Files (5 of 5 boxes), 1990-1993 (Offsite-box 24, Folder 1-50)
    Includes, among other subjects, "Make Your Own Board Game!"; Thomas Cole exhibition education budget (1992); after-school workshop for educators presented by curator of manuscripts Margaret Heilbrun; proposed permanent gallery re-installation (1992); World War II film program; "Writing History: Works and Process" series; Anne Dillard reading; "Repossessing History" slide show and discussion; programs in connection with City Hall exhibition; "Reinterpreting the American West" symposium; budgets, statistics, and internal memos.
  - Exhibition Files (1 of 2 boxes), 1941-1988 (Offsite-box 25, Folder 1-31)
    This box and the next includes a set of files that appear to be those of volunteer coordinator Jane Lattes. The files are alphabetical by exhibition. They include various documents about the exhibition, including press releases, checklists, reference material, etc., but more relevant to this record group is that many of the files hold docent training notes, tour notes, background material prepared by N-YHS staff, program tie-ins, etc. Those files that include program-related documents in this box are: Rise & Fall of New York; P.T. Barnum; Bellow, Bobbins & Butter Churns; Centuries of Childhood; George Catlin (1941-42); Small Talk; Merchants & Mandarins / New York & the China Trade; Government by Choice: Inventing the U.S. Constitution (and other Constitution bicentennial programs); and Jasper Cropsey. In addition to the 1940s Catlin material, the box holds some photographs of models of antique cars from the collection, possibly dating from the 1950s, and some old reprints of articles.
  - Exhibition Files (2 of 2 boxes), 1983-1989 (Offsite-box 26, Folder 1-40)
    Those files that include program-related documents in this box are: domestic life (Bellows, Bobbins and American Gadgets & Gastronomy); Francis Edmonds; Firefighting on Parade; Glass & Paperweights; Heraldry; Hudson River & the Highlands; immigration conference; Jackie Robinson; Karol Kozlowski; Livingston Manor; lecture series; Arnold Newman; Niagara; Paris 1889; Liberty's Legacy; Visions of Liberty; A Child's World; and George Washington in New York.
  - General Education & Tours Files (1 of 7 boxes), 1979-1992 (Offsite-box 28, Folder 1-52)
    These seven boxes include files that appear to have been primarily those of volunteer coordinators and associates for school programs, Jane Lattes, Marion Galison and Judith Giuriceo. This first box includes files related to specific exhibitions or galleries; these are in alphabetical order and continue in the next box. Principal subjects in this box are AIDS quilt; architecture (McKim, Mead & White); Audubon; Thomas Jefferson Bryan; Andrew Carnegie; Carriage and Volunteer Fire Department Galleries; colonial New York; Art What Thou Eat/Food.
  - General Education & Tours Files (2 of 7 boxes), 1985-1992 (Offsite-box 29, Folder 1-59)
    This box concludes the files related to specific exhibitions or galleries. Principal subjects are Forever Wild (Adirondacks); Highlights Tour; Hudson River School; Luman Reed Gallery/Thomas Cole (includes synopsis of curator Tim Burgard's training session for volunteers about Course of Empire); Paris 1889; Peale; Silver; Tenth Street Studio (proposed exhibition); unguided group introductory script; World War II Home Front. The box also holds material on various subjects compiled here as they relate to paintings: Changing Face of Portraiture; Early American Leaders / Presidents, Patriots & Portraits; landscapes; frames; and American genre (includes transcript of curator Ella Foshay's talk to the volunteers about genre paintings).
  - General Education & Tours Files (3 of 7 boxes), 1968-1992 (Offsite-box 30, Folder 1-61)
    This box includes files on education programs more generally, including teacher workshops, open houses, letters from student visitors, school program publicity packets, teachers' center, adult and child versions of a slide show script (1986), and other actual and proposed programs. Also includes files concerning contacts with particular schools or other institutions, especially Junior League, but also Community School District 5, Symphony Space, and others.
  - General Education & Tours Files (4 of 7 boxes), 1985-1992 (Offsite-box 31, Folder 1-81)